{"tossups": [{"question": "The 1580s war for this country\u2019s succession included the Battle of Ponta Delgada, a naval battle nearly 1,000 miles west of this country. In 1419, this country claimed the island of Porto Santo, part of an archipelago that is now an autonomous region with capital Funchal. Madeira and the Azores are controlled by this country, where the Douro River empties into the Atlantic near Porto. A 1755 earthquake and fire devastated, for ten points, what country\u2019s capital city of Lisbon?", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man worked with the ambassador Michel Ange Bernard de Mangourit during his most famous venture, which began when he arrived aboard the<em> Embuscade</em> in Charleston Harbor. This man attempted to hire the<em> Anti-George</em> and other privateers to help his country in a war against Spain and Britain, a stance opposed by George Washington. For ten points, name this Frenchman whose namesake affair tested American neutrality.", "answer": "Edmond-Charles<b> Gen\u02c6et</b> (accept Citizen<b> Gen\u02c6et</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Louise Stanley led this department\u2019s Bureau of Home Economics, which produced the<em> Aunt Sammy</em> radio program from 1926 to 1944 and the first ever braille cookbook. Under Abraham Lincoln, Isaac Newton was the first head of what would become this department. The SNAP aid program is administered by this department, which was led by former Iowa governor Tom Vilsack in the Obama administration. For ten points, name this Cabinet department that runs the Farm Service Agency.", "answer": "United States Department of<b> Agriculture</b> (accept<b> USDA</b>) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man described and names a type of beauty contest where the judges rate based on how they think other people will rate. This man, who proposed that it may be economically productive to pay people to bury and dig up money, famously criticized the punitive measures found in the Treaty of Versailles in his book<em> The Economic Consequences of the Peace</em>. For ten points, name this author of<em> The General Theory</em> <em>of Employment, Interest and Money</em>, an early 20th century British economist.", "answer": "John Maynard<b> Keynes</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "In 1922 in this city, a mob of boys brawled with dock workers who were wearing straw hats two days before the traditional date on which they became unfashionable. The Straw Hat Riot took place in this city, where youths living in dumbbell tenements were photographed in Jacob Riis\u2019<em> How the Other Half</em> <em>Lives</em>. Young men, predominantly Irish, in this city who were unable to afford a $300 fee rioted during the Civil War. For ten points, name this city where a 1935 race riot killed three people in Harlem.", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (or<b> NY</b>C)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man once offered 500 pounds for the purchase of the twelve-year-old girl Teresa Makri, a failed bid that led to his poem \u201cMaid of Athens, ere we part.\u201d After meeting his cousin at a ball, he compared her to \u201cthe night of cloudless climes and starry skies\u201d in another poem. This man, who described the travels of a disillusioned man in<em> Childe Harold\u2019s Pilgrimage</em>, died in Missolonghi in 1824. \u201cShe Walks in Beauty\u201d and<em> Don Juan</em> [JOO-un] were written by, for ten points, what English poet who died fighting in the Greek War of Independence?", "answer": "Lord George Gordon<b> Byron</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "The territory that became this state was governed by the Howell Code and Hoyt Code. Jesuit Father Eusebio Francisco Kino worked with Native Americans in this state at Mission San Xavier del Bac. In 1917, the Phelps Dodge corporation deported many mine workers from this state\u2019s town of Bisbee. In 2011, a congresswoman from this state resigned after being shot in an assassination attempt. For ten points, name this southwest state where Teddy Roosevelt supported the creation of Petrified Forest and Grand Canyon National Parks.", "answer": "<b> Arizona</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this first socialist president of France.", "answer": "Francois<b> Mitterand</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The musicians Stobrod and Pangle are deserters from this war in a film that focuses on the love of Ada for carpenter W.P. Inman, who enlists in it. Sergio Leone\u2019s<em> The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</em> is set against the backdrop of this war, as is<em> Cold Mountain</em>. Denzel Washington stars as Silas Tripp in<em> Glory</em>, in which he takes up his regiment\u2019s flag at the Siege of Fort Wagner during this war. For ten points, name this war, the subject of films like<em> Andersonville</em> and<em> Gettysburg</em>.", "answer": "US<b> Civil</b> War BONUS:<em> Andersonville</em> and<em> Gettysburg</em> were produced by this Civil War buff who founded CNN. ANSWER: Robert Edward \u201cTed\u201d<b> Turner</b> Page 3", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s daughter Alix married Theobald the Good, who had attempted to abduct this woman herself for marriage. This woman allegedly chose the gravesite of Mary Magdalene as her departing point during the Second Crusade. This woman annulled her marriage to Louis VII before marrying a king who imprisoned her for 16 years following a failed revolt that she planned with her sons John and Richard the Lionheart. For ten points, name this 12th century queen consort of England, a noblewoman from Aquitaine.", "answer": "<b> Eleanor</b> of Aquitaine", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An artist from this country created a hyper-realistic sculpture of a pope being struck by a meteorite titled<em> The Ninth Hour</em>. Another artist from this country painted v-shaped rays of light emanating from a street light; that artist helped lead a movement whose manifesto declares that \u201ca racing car is more beautiful than the<em> Victory of Samothrace</em>.\u201d For ten points, name this home country of the 20th century art movement Futurism, which was led by Giacomo Balla and Filippo Marinetti.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this last imperial Chinese dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Qing</b> [cheeng] Dynasty (accept<b> Manchu</b> Dynasty)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Before a battle in this war, a general deployed his stronger troops to the wings at the</b> <b>last second, leading to the \u201creverse\u201d formation of an earlier battle that caused the city</b> <b>of Capua to change sides. This war included a siege where (+)</b> <b>Archimedes legendarily</b> <b>deployed heat rays and ship-destroying claws. A general in this war lit fires far from his</b> <b>location in a swamp to lay an ambush in the Battle of (*)</b> Lake Trasimene; in response, the other side adopted the Fabian strategy. The disastrous military loss at Cannae nearly doomed Rome in, for ten points, what war against Carthage and Hannibal?", "answer": "<b> Second Punic</b> War (prompt on Punic War(s))", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The coup d\u2019etat that brought this family to power shares its</b> <b>name with an Egyptian movement a year later; this family\u2019s Corrective Revolution purged</b> <b>followers of (+)</b> <b>Salah Jadid from the country\u2019s Baath Party. The current head of this</b> <b>Alawite family is overseeing a nine year long (*)</b> civil war that broke out during the Arab Spring. For ten points, name this family whose members, including Hafez and Bashar, have controlled the Syria for nearly five decades.", "answer": "al-<b>Assad</b> family", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The Paw Paw Tunnel is used on one of these structures engineered by Benjamin Wright.</b> <b>A dispute over right of way between one of these structures and the Baltimore and Ohio</b> <b>Railroad was agreed to at the Point of Rocks. (+)</b> <b>Coal from the Alleghenies was brought</b> <b>to Cumberland via one of these structures, the (*)</b> Chesapeake and Ohio. George Washington\u2019s Patowmack Company built five of these structures to improve navigation on the Potomac River. \u201cClinton\u2019s Folly\u201d was, for ten points, what type of structure that terminated at Lake Erie?", "answer": "<b> canal</b>s (accept Chesapeake and Ohio<b> Canal</b>; accept Patowmack<b> Canal</b>; accept Erie<b> Canal</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this year, an investigation by Clarkson Potter found evidence of bribery in the Cipher dispatches. The highest voter turnout in American presidential history took place during this year, whose candidates included a man who had gained fame for breaking up the (+) Canal Ring. The Republican candidate in this year was granted twenty (*)</b> disputed electoral votes and became president after he agreed to bring an end to Reconstruction. For ten points, name this election year in which Samuel Tilden won the popular vote but lost to Rutherford B. Hayes.", "answer": "US presidential election of<b> 1876</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Three Disasters of Wu were a set of attempted persecutions of this religion. During a revival of this religion in Dalit, B.R. Ambedkar began implementing mass conversion</b> <b>to this religion. Prince (+)</b> <b>Shotoku developed this religion in Japan, and the Rock and</b> <b>Pillar Edicts are early evidence of this religion in India, where the (*)</b> Kalinga War convinced Ashoka to convert to this religion. This religion\u2019s founder was born in modern day Nepal and gained enlightenment while sitting under the Bodhi tree. For ten points, name this Indian religion founded by Siddartha Gautama.", "answer": "<b> Buddhism</b> (accept word forms)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This man introduced the phrase \u201cPeace at Home, Peace in the World,\u201d which became part of his country\u2019s foreign policy. This developer of Sun Language Theory gave the Kastamonu Speech while wearing a Panama hat. This leader, who invited John (+) Dewey to reform his nation\u2019s education system, extended voting rights to women and forced Greeks and (*) </b> Armenians to take on new last names. This leader\u2019s reforms included abolishing the caliphate and banning the fez. Secularism was one of the Six Arrows of, for ten points, what World War I hero who served as the first President of Turkey?", "answer": "Mustafa<b> Kemal Ataturk</b> (accept either or both names) ", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Despite being ordered to leave by Herbert Kitchener, this author of</b><em><b> Ian Hamilton\u2019s </b><b>March</b></em><b> rode with the 21st Lancers at the Battle of Omdurman, an experience he later recounted in</b><em><b> The River War</b></em><b>. This (+) Nobel Prize winning author of a four volume </b><em><b>History of the English-Speaking Peoples</b></em><b> wrote that he and his countrymen needed to (*)</b> \u201cbear ourselves\u201d that, if their country would \u201clast for a thousand years, men will still say\u2018This was their finest hour.\u2019\u201d For ten points, name this orator and Prime Minister of Great Britain during World War II.", "answer": "Sir Winston<b> Churchill</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}